<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><study id="54697">  <accessState>      </accessState>  <addInfo />  <availability>    <availability id="54708">      <availability>        A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.      </availability>      <language>        de      </language>      <study ref="../.." />    </availability>    <availability id="54707">      <availability>        A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.      </availability>      <language>        en      </language>      <study ref="../.." />    </availability>  </availability>  <classifications>    <classification id="10296">      <identifier>              </identifier>      <language>        de      </language>      <term>        Gesellschaft, Kultur      </term>      <thesaurus>        ZA Kategorien      </thesaurus>    </classification>    <classification id="10297">      <identifier>              </identifier>      <language>        en      </language>      <term>        Society, Culture      </term>      <thesaurus>        ZA Kategorien      </thesaurus>    </classification>  </classifications>  <collectionDateFormal />  <collectionDates>    <collectionDate id="108541">      <language>        en      </language>      <period>        1978 - 1993      </period>      <study ref="../.." />    </collectionDate>    <collectionDate id="54715">      <language>        de      </language>      <period>        1978 - 1993      </period>      <study ref="../.." />    </collectionDate>  </collectionDates>  <collectionModes>    <collectionMode id="54713">      <language>        de      </language>      <mode>        Mündliche Befragung mit standardisiertem Fragebogen      </mode>      <study ref="../.." />    </collectionMode>    <collectionMode id="54714">      <language>        en      </language>      <mode>        Oral survey with standardized questionnaire      </mode>      <study ref="../.." />    </collectionMode>  </collectionModes>  <controlledKeywords />  <currentVersion>    1.0.0  </currentVersion>  <dataCollectors>    <dataCollector id="108539">      <language>        de      </language>      <name>        INFRATEST, München; Zentralinstitut für Jugendforschung (ZIJ), Leipzig      </name>      <study ref="../.." />    </dataCollector>    <dataCollector id="54698">      <language>        en      </language>      <name>        INFRATEST, Muenchen; Zentralinstitut fuer Jugendforschung (ZIJ), Leipzig      </name>      <study ref="../.." />    </dataCollector>  </dataCollectors>  <dataSets>    <dataSet id="54700">      <fileFormat>        OSIRIS, SPSS      </fileFormat>      <numberUnits>        12447      </numberUnits>      <numberVariables>        442      </numberVariables>      <resourceType>              </resourceType>      <study ref="../.." />      <unitType>              </unitType>    </dataSet>  </dataSets>  <doi>    doi:10.4232/1.2933  </doi>  <doiProposal>    doi:10.4232/1.2933  </doiProposal>  <dsoffset>      </dsoffset>  <fingerprint>      </fingerprint>  <fingerprintMethod>      </fingerprintMethod>  <freeKeywords />  <issueNumber>      </issueNumber>  <issued>    2010-04-13 00:00:00.0 MESZ  </issued>  <language>      </language>  <links />  <notes>    <note id="54705">      <language>        de      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <text>        In die Kumulation wurden all diejenigen Variablen aufgenommen,die zu mindestens zwei Erhebungszeitpunkten gefragt wordensind. Enthalten sind Variablen aus den Einzelerhebungen von1978 (ZA-Studien-Nr. 1141), 1980 (ZA-Studien-Nr. 1142), 1984(ZA-Studien-Nr. 1339), 1988 (ZA-Studien-Nr.1839), 1990 nur neueBundesländer (ZA-Studien-Nr. 2121) und 1993 (ZA-Studien-Nr.2792). Die Einzelstudien bleiben auch weiterhin erhältlich.      </text>    </note>    <note id="54706">      <language>        en      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <text>        All those variables were taken into the cumulationthat were asked on at least two survey times. Containedare variables from individual surveys of1978 (ZA Study No. 1141), 1980 (ZA Study No. 1142), 1984(ZA Study No. 1339), 1988 (ZA Study No.1839), 1990 only newstates (ZA Study No. 2121) and 1993 (ZA Study No.  2792).The individual studys still remain available.      </text>    </note>  </notes>  <principalInvestigators>    <principalInvestigator id="116875">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Lang, Sabine      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116878">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Volkert, Marieke      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116882">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Müller-Andritzky, Maria      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116963">      <affiliation>        Sonderforschungsbereich 3 der Universitäten Frankfurt und Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Glatzer, Wolfgang      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116965">      <affiliation>        Sonderforschungsbereich 3 der Universitäten Frankfurt und Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Zapf, Wolfgang      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116880">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Habich, Roland      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="153129">      <affiliation>        Wissenschaftszentrum Berlin      </affiliation>      <name>        Spellerberg, Annette      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116876">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Gransche, Elisabeth      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116881">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Glatzer, Wolfgang      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="117262">      <affiliation>        ZUMA, Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Noll, Heinz-Herbert      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116883">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Noll, Heinz-Herbert      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116874">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Brachtl, Wolfgang      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116879">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Zapf, Wolfgang      </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="49086">      <affiliation>        Zentralinstitut für Jugendforschung (ZIJ), Leipzig      </affiliation>      <name>              </name>    </principalInvestigator>    <principalInvestigator id="116877">      <affiliation>        Universität Mannheim      </affiliation>      <name>        Siara, Christian S.      </name>    </principalInvestigator>  </principalInvestigators>  <priorVersions />  <publicationAgent id="2447">    <contactPerson>      Brigitte Hausstein    </contactPerson>    <email>      Brigitte.Hausstein@gesis.org    </email>    <homepage>      http://www.gesis.org/    </homepage>    <logo>      /dara/fileadmin/doi/Dateien/GESIS_Logo_51x20.jpg    </logo>    <name>      GESIS - Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften    </name>    <prefix />    <suffixstart />  </publicationAgent>  <publicationDate />  <publicationPlace />  <publications />  <regAgency id="2443">    <contactPerson>      Brigitte Hausstein    </contactPerson>    <email>      Brigitte.Hausstein@gesis.org    </email>    <homepage>      http://www.gesis.org    </homepage>    <name>      GESIS - Leibniz-Institut für Sozialwissenschaften    </name>  </regAgency>  <relatedIDs />  <rights />  <selectionMethods>    <selectionMethod id="54710">      <language>        en      </language>      <method>        Multi-stage stratified random sample (ADM mastersample) among all German citizens living in private households 18 years old and older. In 1990 in the new states selection took place as follows: on the first stage a random selection among the whole of the population eligible to vote from the central resident card file: determination of survey household through an attached random route procedure.      </method>      <study ref="../.." />    </selectionMethod>    <selectionMethod id="54709">      <language>        de      </language>      <method>        Mehrstufig geschichtete Zufallsauswahl (ADM-Mastersample) 1990 wurde in den neuen Bundesländern wie folgt ausgewählt: auf der ersten Stufe Zufallsauswahl aus der Gesamtheit der wahlberechtigten Bevölkerung aus der zentralen Einwohnerkartei: Ermittlung des Befragungshaushaltes durch ein angehängtes Random-Route-Verfahren.      </method>      <study ref="../.." />    </selectionMethod>  </selectionMethods>  <sizes />  <studyId>    ZA2933  </studyId>  <summary>    <summary id="54704">      <language>        de      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <text>        Tatsächliche Lebensbedingungen und subjektiv empfundeneLebensqualität der Bevölkerung. Kumulation derWohlfahrtssurveys 1978 bis 1993.Themen: 1. Einschätzung von Zukunftsperspektiven:Zufriedenheit mit dem Lebensstandard; pessimistische oderoptimistische Erwartungen bezüglich der Entwicklungausgewählter Lebensbereiche; optimistische Zukunftserwartung.2. Politische Einstellungen und politische Partizipation:Eigene politische Einflußnahme; Politikinteresse; Zufriedenheitmit den Möglichkeiten politischer Betätigung; konservative oderprogressive Lebenseinstellung; Postmaterialismus;Parteipräferenz.3. Einstellungen zu sozialer Ungleichheit und zumWohlfahrtsstaat: Wahrgenommene Konfliktlinien zwischengesellschaftlichen Gruppen; Demokratiezufriedenheit;Zufriedenheit mit der Demokratie, der öffentlichen Sicherheit,dem Umweltschutz und dem sozialen Netz; allgemeinesGlücksgefühl; Lebenszufriedenheit im Zeitvergleich mit derVergangenheit und Zukunft; Häufigkeit eigener Arbeitslosigkeitund Beurteilung der finanziellen Absicherung beiArbeitslosigkeit.4. Familie und Erziehung: Verständnis beim Partner undZufriedenheit mit der Partnerschaft (Interviewerrating:Anwesenheit des Partners bei Beantwortung dieser Frage);Ausbildungszufriedenheit; Wunsch nach anderer Ausbildung;Zufriedenheit mit dem Status als Hausfrau und Gründe für dieArbeit als Hausfrau; Beurteilung der Chancen, zu neuenKontakten zu kommen; Beeinträchtigung des Wohlbefindens durchMeinungsverschiedenheiten in der Familie oder durch Streit mitNachbarn, Freunden oder Kollegen; Wichtigkeit ausgewählterLebensbereiche für das Wohlbefinden und die allgemeineLebenszufriedenheit; Wichtigkeit von Beruf, Freizeit undFamilie; Überforderung durch die Arbeit.5. Einstellung zu Abtreibung, Erziehungsgeld, Sterbehilfe undGesundheit allgemein: Einstellung zum Erziehungsgeld und zurgesetzlichen Regelung der Schwangerschaftsunterbrechung;Einstellung zur Sterbehilfe; Gesundheitszufriedenheit(Skalometer); Arztbesuche in der letzten Zeit;Lebensumstellungen und Berufsumstellungen aufgrund vonKrankheit oder Behinderung; Medikamentenkonsum;Charakterisierung der psychischen und physischen Situation(Skala).6. Wichtigkeitseinstufungen von Lebensbereichen undBerufsmerkmalen: Wohnzufriedenheit (Skalometer); Beurteilungder Wohnungsqualität und Zufriedenheit mit der Wohngegend(Skalometer); Lebenszufriedenheit (Skalometer); Zufriedenheitmit der Haushaltsführung; Zufriedenheit mit der Freizeit;Umfang der Freizeit; Zufriedenheit mit der eigenen Karriere;Einkommenszufriedenheit im Zeitvergleich und Vergleich zuFreunden sowie zum Durchschnittseinkommen; Einschätzung dereigenen Arbeitsmarktchancen; wichtigste Anforderungen an einenidealen Arbeitsplatz und Vergleich dieser Kriterien mit deraktuellen Situation am Arbeitsplatz; Zufriedenheit mit derArbeitsaufteilung im Haushalt; prozentuale Aufteilung derArbeit im Haushalt auf den Befragten, den Ehepartner, dieKinder und weitere Haushaltsmitglieder; empfundene Belastungdes Befragten durch Beruf und Haushalt sowie vermuteteBelastung des Ehepartners; weitere bezahlte Nebentätigkeitenoder weiterer Hauptberuf; unbezahlter Hauptberuf und unbezahlteNebentätigkeiten sowie bezahlte Gelegenheitsarbeit und Hilfebei Nachbarn, Freunden und Verwandten; bezahltelandwirtschaftliche Tätigkeit und ehrenamtliche Tätigkeiten;Erleben eines besonders glücklichen bzw. leidvollen Ereignissesim Leben; Aufteilung und Erledigung von Tätigkeiten im Haushaltsowie Reparaturarbeiten, Renovierungsarbeiten,Verschönerungsarbeiten durch Haushaltsmitglieder, Verwandte,Nachbarn bzw. Firmen; Hilfeleistungen von Verwandten, Freundenund Nachbarn.7. Religiosität und Kirchlichkeit: Kirchgangshäufigkeit undZufriedenheit mit der Kirche.8. Wahrgenommene Umweltbelastungen: EmpfundeneUmweltbelastungen durch Lärm, Luftverschmutzung,Grünflächenmangel und Landschaftszerstörung; Besorgnis überWasserverschmutzung, Meeresschädigung, Luftverschmutzung,unsachgemäße Beseitigung von chemischen Industrieabfällen unddie Beseitigung von radioaktivem Müll; Beurteilung der Reinheitdes Leitungswassers.9. Anomia.10. Demographische Angaben zur Person des Befragten: Fragenzum Bereich Staatsangehörigkeit, Aufenthaltsdauer, Wohnung,Wohnort, weitere Angaben über Haushaltszusammensetzung undKinder des Befragten, Selbsteinschätzung derSchichtzugehörigkeit, Kurzarbeit, Weiterbildung, Gründe fürNichterwerbstätigkeit, erwartete Verbesserung derEinkommenssituation; perzipierte Möglichkeiten, eineArbeitsstelle zu finden; Wunsch nach Berufstätigkeit; Dauer dergesamten Berufstätigkeit und nach Beendigung derBerufstätigkeit; Furcht vor Arbeitslosigkeit undStellenwechsel; Berufsprestigeskala; soziale Herkunft;Zimmerzahl; Toilette und Bad innerhalb der Wohnung;Zentralheizung; Wohnstatus; Miethöhe; Haustyp; Wohnen imHochhaus; Ortstyp; Gemeindegröße; Zufriedenheit mit denKleinkindern im Haushalt; Pflegebedürftige im Haushalt; Kinderim Heim oder in einer Pflegeeinrichtung; sonstige Verwandte ineinem Heim bzw. Pflegeeinrichtung; Freunde oder Freundschaften;Häufigkeit des Treffens mit Freunden.11. Daten über Freunde und Bekannte.12. Mitgliedschaften in Organisationen und Vereinen:Gewerkschaftsmitgliedschaft; Parteimitgliedschaft;Mitgliedschaft in Bürgerinitiativen, kirchlichen Vereinen,Sportvereinen sowie Gesangsvereinen; Engagement im Verein durchWortmeldung.13. Angaben zum Interview-Verlauf: Interviewort; Anwesenheitanderer Personen beim Interview und deren Verwandtschaftsgradzum Befragten; Eingriff Dritter in das Interview;Interviewunterbrechung; Kooperationsbereitschaft undGlaubwürdigkeit des Befragten; Interviewbeginn; Interviewende.      </text>    </summary>    <summary id="54703">      <language>        en      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <text>        Actual living conditions and subjectively perceived quality of life ofthe population. Cumulation of the welfare surveys 1978 to 1993.Topics: 1. Assessment of future prospects: satisfaction with standardof living; pessimistic or optimistic expectations regarding developmentof selected areas of life; optimistic future expectation.2. Political attitudes and political participation: personal politicalinfluence; interest in politics; satisfaction with possibilities ofpolitical activity; conservative or progressive attitude to life;postmaterialism; party preference.3. Attitudes to social inequality and the welfare state: perceivedlines of conflict between social groups; satisfaction with democracy,public safety, environmental protection and the social net; generalfeeling of happiness; contentment with life in comparison over timewith past and future; frequency of personal unemployment and judgementon financial security in case of unemployment.4. Family and education: understanding with partner and satisfactionwith partnership (interviewer rating: presence of partner whileanswering this question); satisfaction with education; desire for othereducation; satisfaction with status as housewife and reasons for workas housewife; judgement on the chances of new contacts; disturbance ofwell-being from differences of opinion in one´s family or quarrel withneighbors, friends or colleagues; importance of selected areas of lifefor well-being and general contentment with life; importance ofoccupation, leisure time and family; work asking too much.5. Attitude to abortion, the child benefit, aid to those wanting todie and health in general: attitude to the child benefit and the legalregulation of abortion; attitude to aid to those wanting to die; healthsatisfaction (scale); visits to the doctor in recent time; life changesand occupation changes due to illness or disability; use of medication;characterization of psychological and physical situation (scale).6. Importance classification of areas of life and occupationalcharacteristics: satisfaction with housing (scale); judgement onresidence quality and satisfaction with residential area (scale);contentment with life (scale); satisfaction with housekeeping;satisfaction with leisure time; extent of leisure time; satisfactionwith personal career; satisfaction with income in comparison over timeand comparison with friends as well as average income; assessment ofpersonal job market chances; most important demands of an ideal job andcomparison of these criteria with current situation at work;satisfaction with division of work in household; percent division ofwork in household among respondent, spouse, children and furthermembers of household; perceived burden of respondent from occupationand household as well as assumed burden of spouse; further paid sidejobs or further primary occupation; unpaid primary occupation andunpaid side jobs as well as paid casual work and help with neighbors,friends and relatives; paid agricultural activity and honoraryactivities; experiencing a particularly happy or unfortunate event inlife; division and carrying out activities in household as well asrepair jobs, renovation work, improvement work by members of household,relatives, neighbors or businesses; assistance from relatives, friendsand neighbors.7. Religiousness and devotion: frequency of church attendance andsatisfaction with church.8. Perceived environmental pollution: perceived environmentalpollution from noise, air pollution, shortage of green areas anddestruction of countryside; concern about water pollution, harm to theocean, air pollution, improper elimination of chemical industry wastesand the elimination of radioactive waste; judgement on the purity oftap water.$9. Anomia.10. Demographic information on person of respondent: questions on thearea nationality, length of stay, residence, place of residence,further information on composition of household and children ofrespondent, self-assessment of social class, short time work, furthereducation, reasons for not being employed, expected improvement inincome situation; perceived possibilities to find work; desire foremployment; duration of entire employment and after discontinuation ofemployment; fear of unemployment and change of position; occupationalprestige scale; social origins; number of rooms; toilet and bath withinresidence; central heating; residential status; amount of rent; type ofbuilding; living in high-rise; type of city; size of municipality;satisfaction with babies in household; someone in need of nursing carein household; children in home or care facility; other relatives inhome or care facility; friends or friendships; frequency of meetingwith friends.$11. Data on friends and acquaintances.12. Memberships in organizations and clubs: union membership; partymembership; membership in citizen initiatives, church clubs, sportclubs as well as choral societies; involvement in the club throughrequest to speak.13. Information on course of interview: place of interview; presenceof other persons during interview and their degree of relationship torespondent; intervention of others in interview; interruption ofinterview; willingness to cooperate and credibility of respondent;start of interview; end of interview.      </text>    </summary>  </summary>  <titles>    <title id="54702">      <language>        de      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <title>        Wohlfahrtssurveys 1978 - 1993 (Kumulierter Datensatz)      </title>    </title>    <title id="54701">      <language>        en      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <title>        Welfare Surveys 1978 to 1993 (Cumulated Data Set)      </title>    </title>  </titles>  <translatedTitles />  <universes>    <universe id="54711">      <areaControlled>              </areaControlled>      <areaFree>        Research area: FRG      </areaFree>      <language>        en      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <universe>        Research area: FRG      </universe>    </universe>    <universe id="54712">      <areaControlled>              </areaControlled>      <areaFree>        In Privathaushalten lebende deutsche Staatsangehörige ab 18 Jahren      </areaFree>      <language>        de      </language>      <study ref="../.." />      <universe>        In Privathaushalten lebende deutsche Staatsangehörige ab 18 Jahren      </universe>    </universe>  </universes>  <urls>    <dataURL id="54699">      <dataURL>        http://info1.gesis.org/dbksearch13/sdesc2.asp?no=2933&amp;db=e&amp;doi=10.4232/1.2933      </dataURL>      <study ref="../.." />    </dataURL>  </urls></study>