<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><OAI-PMH xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2012-07-11T11:41:20Z</responseDate><request metadataPrefix="oai_wgl" identifier="oai:gesis.izsoz.de:25527" verb="GetRecord">http://www.ssoar.info/ssoar/OAIHandler</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:gesis.izsoz.de:25527</identifier><datestamp>2011-06-27T10:39:00Z</datestamp><setSpec>SSOAR</setSpec></header><metadata><oai_wgl:oai_wglType xmlns:oai_wgl="http://multiweb.gesis.org/leibnizrepository/schema/oai_wgl/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:wgl="http://multiweb.gesis.org/leibnizrepository/schema/wgl_dc/" xsi:schemaLocation="http://multiweb.gesis.org/leibnizrepository/schema/oai_wgl/ http://multiweb.gesis.org/leibnizrepository/schema/oai_wgl.xsd">25527<wgl:identifier>http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0168-ssoar-255276</wgl:identifier><wgl:identifier>1573-0751</wgl:identifier><wgl:date>2010</wgl:date><wgl:title>Pride and prejudice: comparative corruption research and the British case</wgl:title><wgl:creator>Xenakis, Sappho</wgl:creator><wgl:wglcontributor>http://www.peerproject.eu/</wgl:wglcontributor><wgl:type>Zeitschriftenartikel</wgl:type><wgl:wgltype>Zeitschriftenartikel</wgl:wgltype><wgl:description>In recent years, comparative corruption analysis has been fuelled by the growth of international survey data on related perceptions. Taking issue with the typological vein of such analysis, this article questions both the treatment of perceptions indices and the validity and pertinence of variables used to explain them. It is argued that perceptions are conflated with practice, whilst explanatory variables appear ungrounded in empirical reality. These limitations serve to reinforce expectations that corruption is a menace to be associated primarily with societies of the global periphery. Drawing on the supposedly paradigmatic case of Britain, the article suggests that the problem of bias in comparative scholarship is compounded by three factors: the failure of comparative and domestic-focused literatures to engage with one another in sufficient depth; the relative lack of qualitative research into corruption within core Western states; and the neglect of power in the study of perceptions and practices at comparative and domestic-focused levels of analysis.</wgl:description><wgl:language>Englisch</wgl:language><wgl:rights>PEER Licence Agreement (applicable only to documents from PEER project)</wgl:rights><wgl:source>Crime, Law and Social Change, Jg. 54, H. 1, S. 39-61</wgl:source><wgl:contributor>SSOAR - Social Science Open Access Repository</wgl:contributor><wgl:wglsubject>Sozialwissenschaften</wgl:wglsubject></oai_wgl:oai_wglType></metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>